all right I promised a while back that
I'd film a video that that further
explained this I think I called it this
single leg abducted Romanian deadlift um
it's it's a difficult exercise to name
but I want to discuss some things uh
first of all there are good single leg
movements like a single leg you know a
pistol squat a single leg box squat
where you're really on one leg okay and
also the single leg RL single leg RDL
you know I come back come up I'm really
on one leg those are true single leg
exercises and then there are exercises
like a Bulgarian split squat we say this
is a single leg
exercise you
know this here when really it's a double
leg exercise you're just widening your
Bas of support you are getting stability
for this back leg but you intend to have
most of the weight on this leg on this
front leg but this leg helps with
stability now when you perform a b
gearan split squat because of the way
the kinematics because of the kinematics
of the lift you get stability from that
back leg throughout the whole range of
movement
so right here my hip flexors are
stretched I'm very stable right here as
I come down my hip flexor stays
stretched
I'm still stable here and I come up but
if you try the same thing in a deadlift
pattern what happens is you put your
back leg up you're very stable right
here and then as you come
down now this leg all of a sudden
becomes slack that rear leg does not
give you stability anymore so what's the
point then it Alters your kinematics
because you're trying to get stability
from that back leg you end up doing
something like you know trying to round
over more because if you sink back more
you get less and less stability from
this leg
so um if you want to perform good form
good kinematics where you sit back this
is not a good option to do a Bulgarian
single leg Romanian deadlift but I did
find that the solution for me
was you still want you know the leg RDL
just like the pistol squat great
movement or the single legegg squat you
should still do them but the the the
benefit of the Bulgarian Squad is
because of this extra stability you can
throw a barbell or hold on to heavy
dumbbells and you can go really heavy
with the lift well same thing with this
single leg rvl you know some people are
very coord can go really heavy but if
you you know place the other the non
working leg onto something you get a lot
more stability and now you can generate
more force with the prime mover so if if
I was to just purely out this leg then
the barell barbell would collide with
this box so I've got to scan out a
little bit now first I'll show you with
a catle bell and then with a barbell so
this leg stays in line I'm not moving it
around the focus of this you want to be
moving at the hips come down come up
so I start here sit
back this kettle bell stays in line with
the feet come up now is this leg helping
it is a little bit but I'm just like in
a Bulgarian split squat I'm trying to
not let it help that much I'm trying to
limit the amount I'm just use that for
stability I'm not trying to you know
lift the weight up with this leg just
like the same thing you do in a
Bulgarian split Squad so with the
barbell what I do is place this near the
Box okay
abduct all right um if I was using if I
have weight on the bar I'll position
this just like I would in a regular
Romanian deadlift um or a deadlift I
would have it close to my shins and
again from here just come
up so the bar comes close to that box I
keep an arch I sit back come up and the
focus you'd want to do it just as if you
were doing a single leg Aral but just
with some added stability so it's not a
true single leg exercise it's really a a
double leg exercise the focus is on one
leg you just get some added stability
and it lets you go a lot heavier you
know I if I go above like 275 pounds
especially when I try like 300 if I just
do a single yard
maybe like one in five reps will feel
coordinated the other ones are kind of
all over the place but when I do this I
found that the very first time I tried
it I felt very controlled and very
comfortable anyway still don't know
really what to call it single leg
abducted RDL but that's not a good name
but I haven't really thought of anything
else but give it a try you might like it